A Guide to the John Malcus Ellison Papers 1941-1979
Archives and Special Collections Department, L. Douglas Wilder Library, Virginia Union University
- Series 5. Writings 1945-1978, About 2000 items
  - Subseries 5.2. History of Virginia Union University, 1000 items
    One of Ellison's retirement goals was to write a definitive history of Virginia Union University and he amassed a wealth of research information in preparation. He began by subdividing his work into decades of history and collecting clippings, photographs, programs, personal histories that he recorded and books written at the turn of the century about African American progress after slavery. Several articles were among his book notes as well as hand-written notes. There is a separate folder of distinguished alumni news. The chapters he used as file labels do not signify actual chapters, but notes and research material related to proposed chapters. Included in chapter one is a typed manuscript of what appears to be chapters one and two.
    - Chapter One (Box-folder 7.187)
    - Chapter Two-VUU Comes Into Existence (Box-folder 7.188)
    - Chapter Three-The Period of Transition and Expansion (Box-folder 7.189)
    - Chapter Five-School of Religion News (Box-folder 7.190)
    - Chapter Seven-Institutional Budget (Box-folder 7.191)
    - Chapter Eight-Decade of the 1940's (Box-folder 7.192)
    - Chapter Nine-The Decade 1950-1960 (Box-folder 7.193)
    - Chapter 10-The Decade 1960-1970 (Box-folder 7.194)
    - Chapter 12-Biographical Sketches (Box-folder 7.195)
    - Chapter 12-Photographs (Box-folder 7.196)
    - Chapter 13-Dr. A. B. James (Box-folder 7.197)
    - Chapters 16-19 Inauguration (Box-folder 7.198)
    - Chapter 20 Appendix (Box-folder 7.199)
    - Drafts and Outlines (Box-folder 7.200)
    - Notes (Box-folder 7.201)
    - Research Materials (Box-folder 7.202)
- Series 6. Pictures 1912-1973, About 20 items
  In preparation for his history of Virginia Union, Ellison collected and duplicated old photos of the Virginia Union and Hartshorn Memorial College faculty and students. The images range from an early Union Football team to faculty events of the 1960's. All but two of the photographs are black and white, and not all of the subjects are identified.
  - Photograph of Southern Education Foundation members and directors at the Annual Meeting in New York April 11, 1963 (Folio PMS-001/1)
  - Color photograph portrait of Ellison 1970 (Folio PMS-001/2)
  - VUU 1912-1920's (Folio PMS-001/3)
  - VUU 1917-1973 (Folio PMS-001/4)
- Series 7. Programs 1936-1979, About 200 items
  With the active personal and professional life that Ellison led, he participated in and attended many programs during his lifetime. He was frequently a guest speaker at local churches in the Richmond area and especially Northumberland County's Shiloh Baptist Church. The vas array of programs are sorted in chronological order by whether Ellison appeared on the program or not.
  - With Ellison (Box-folder 7.203)
  - Without Ellison (Box-folder 7.204)
- Series 8. Awards and Certificates 1950-1979, About 25 items
  There were many awards and recognition memorabilia presented to Ellison, especially as his career wound to a close. The plaques were given by a wide range of admirers, from Union-affiliated groups to churches to national organizations. Ellison received honorary degrees from Virginia Union University (06 June 1950), Morehouse College (07 June 1955) and Virginia State College (30 May 1960).
  - Certificates 1950-1979 (Box-folder 7.205)
  - Honorary Degrees (Box-folder 7.206)
  - Plaques 1955 (Box-folder 7.207)
  - Plaques 1977-1979 (Box-folder 7.208)
  - Southern Education Foundation plaque 1970 (Box-folder 8.209)
  - Afro-American Award plaque 1953 (Box-folder 8.210)
  - St. Stephens Baptist Church plaque (Box-folder 8.211)
  - Miles W. Connor Chapter (Vuu Alumni Assn.) May 5, 1979, Trophy (Box-folder 8.212)
  - Oversize certificates and plaques, oversized (4 certificates and 2 plaques) (Box-folder 8.213)